all right
[Music]
as I noted my video on bone mineral
density vegetarians at slightly lower
bone mineral density in their spines
although the difference was basically
within the margin of error for the test
if the bone quality really is
compromised it could lead to a collapsed
vertebrae increased spinal fracture risk
there's no evidence for this the
incidence of vertebral fracture was
ascertained in older women who had been
vegan for most of their lives 34 years
on average and despite their calcium
intake being terrible about half that of
the non-vegans and a quarter of them
vitamin D deficient the incidence of
vertebral fractures was not
significantly different although the
vegans had a higher prevalence of
vitamin D deficiency and lower dietary
calcium intakes the two factors were not
associated with bone loss in fact the
annual loss in bone marrow density in
the hips of vegans was less than half
that of the meat eaters though the
difference did not reach statistical
significance
vegetarian women had not been found to
be at higher risk of any kind of
fractures including wrist fractures in
this case though among vegetarians those
who consume the least vegetable protein
intake were at the highest risk for
fracture those who ate beans every day
or nuts or like veggie burgers only had
a third of the risk fractures compared
to vegetarians who only ate beans or
other higher protein foods less than
three times a week so those who consume
a vegan or vegetarian diet may be at
increased risk of fracture unless care
is taken to ensure an adequate quantity
and variety of foods high in protein
such as whole grains nuts and beans but
be chickpees or lentils are in the diet
that's one of the reasons my free daily
dozen app I recommend whole grains and
legumes every day
hip fractures are even more serious
those eating legumes like beans every
day reduce their risk of hip fracture by
more than 60 percent compared to 40
lower risk for meat protein with
plant-based Meats coming in in between
with about 50 lower risk of hip
fractures
what's the bottom line on plant-based
diets and bone health according to this
2020 review
theoretically a long-term plant-based
diet May reduce the risk of osteoporosis
but that has yet to be demonstrated what
we do know is that plant-based diets
when ensuring adequate calcium of
vitamin D levels don't appear to have
any detrimental effects on bone health
but this was published August 2020. in
November 2020 the 12-year follow-up to
the study I talked about in my last
video on comparative fracture risk in
vegetarians versus non-vegetarians was
published finding that non-mediators
especially vegans had higher risk of
total bone fractures including at sites
associated with osteoporosis such as hip
fractures
it comes out to be about 20 more cases
in vegans for every thousand people over
10 years so if indeed this is cause and
effect eating vegan there would be a an
annual one in 500 chance of having a
bone fracture that you otherwise might
not have had
was it because they weren't eating
enough beans apparently not since vegans
getting more protein still apparently
had higher risk maybe it was because
they weren't getting enough calcium
apparently not since vegans getting more
calcium still apparently at higher risk
what about bone and vitamin B12 if you
remember epic Oxford where the bone data
comes from is the same group of British
vegans who had rampant B12 deficiency
more than half the vegans were B12
deficient because they weren't
adequately supplementing with B12 or B12
fortified Foods this can lead to high
homocysteine levels which not only
increase stroke risk but may increase
the activity of bone-eating cells this
was in a Petri dish but you do indeed
see low bone mineral density and those
born with a birth defect at least a high
homocysteine levels in the blood
therefore High serum homocysteine may be
regarded as a factor that can reduce
both bone mass and quality but you don't
know until you put it to the test and
homocysteine lowering treatment failed
to reduce the risk of bone fracture so
in the end the effect of B12 deficiency
in bone health remains to be established
okay so how do we explain the higher
fracture rates found among vegans the
investigators conclude that their
findings suggest that bone health and
vegans requires further research but
there were some Clues the elevated
fracture risk both for total fractures
and for hip fractures specifically was
only significant for those under a BMI
of 22.5 which is like under about 130
pounds for a woman of average height so
part of the problem is that vegans tend
to be so Slender on average why are
overweight and obese individuals
protected from fractures well think
about it they have cushioning during a
fall there's more of a cushion on your
hips also there's an enzyme in fatty
tissue that churns out estrogen which is
why women increase their breast cancer
risk a percentage point for every pound
they gain in adulthood but estrogen can
also have a bone preserving effect now
you can get the best of both worlds
consuming soy Foods preventing bone loss
while at the same time associated with
lessening breast cancer risk for both
estrogen receptor positive tumors and
estrogen receptor negative tumors
finally overweight and obese individuals
may also have stronger bones just from
The increased weight bearing carrying
100 extra pounds you're doing major
weight-bearing exercise just walking
across the room
so the risk difference they saw between
vegans and meat eaters were likely at
least partially due to the difference in
BMI my money however is on vitamin D
Great Britain is at Canadian latitudes
the sun's rays are at such an angle
during the winter months up there that
the vitamin D levels among British
vegans in the winter time drops down to
sub-optimal levels ideally we should be
up around 75 nanomoles per liter or 30
nanograms per milliliter depending on
what units you're using which the vegans
nail in the summer it is the sunshine
vitamin after all but in the winter not
getting the vitamin D added to dairy or
found naturally in oily fish if vegans
aren't supplementing at that Latitude
during the winter their vitamin D levels
may drop too low
now randomized controlled trials so that
vitamin D alone does not seem to reduce
fracture rates but boosting people's D
and calcium at the same time does so
maybe it was a combination of the
relatively low D and calcium intakes
among the vegans that led to their
higher fracture rates we won't know for
sure until it's actually put to the test
and what it is you can be sure I'll do a
video about it
[Music]
foreign